<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><feed
  xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:thr="http://purl.org/syndication/thread/1.0"
  xml:lang="en-US"
  xml:base="http://mettacenter.org/wp-atom.php"
   >
	<title type="text">Metta Center &#187; Daily Metta</title>
	<subtitle type="text"></subtitle>

	<updated>2015-06-12T16:09:45Z</updated>

	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mettacenter.org" />
	<id>http://mettacenter.org/feed/atom/</id>
	<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://mettacenter.org/category/daily-metta/feed/atom/" />

	<generator uri="http://wordpress.org/" version="4.2.2">WordPress</generator>
	<entry>
		<author>
			<name>Stephanie Van Hook</name>
					</author>
		<title type="html"><![CDATA[&#8220;Go Deeper, Woodcutter&#8221;&#8211;Daily Metta]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/go-deeper-woodcutter-daily-metta/" />
		<id>http://mettacenter.org/?p=16791</id>
		<updated>2015-06-12T03:23:33Z</updated>
		<published>2015-06-12T03:23:33Z</published>
		<category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="Daily Metta" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="daily metta" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="gandhi" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="inner resources" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="Nonviolence" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="woodcutter" />		<summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>June 12: &#8220;I am but a seeker after Truth.&#8221; &#8211;Gandhi (Young India, June 17, 1926)  Hindu mystic, father of the modern Vedantic movement, Sri Ramakrishna of Dakshineswar, often shared stories with his devotees to illustrate principles important for understanding the nature of Reality, what Gandhi would call, Sat, or Truth with a capital T. The story of the woodcutter and the sage is one of my favorites: There once lived a poor woodcutter. He could not earn a decent living because the trees available to him were not of a very good quality. A sage lived in that forest, and each day would sit under a banyan tree. One day, the woodcutter approached the sage, almost in desperation, and the sage looked at him. The woodcutter peered deeply into his eyes, which seemed to say to him “Go Deeper.” The woodcutter decided he would do just that, and he moved more deeply into the forest and came across sandalwood trees. These trees were very sought after, and the woodcutter only had to work once a week. But he thought about the sage again, and the words would not leave him, “Go Deeper.” So he decided to venture even deeper into the forest, and lo&#8217; and behold, he came across a silver mine! Amazing he thought! His worries were truly over. And some time passed, but again, the sage’s eyes came to his mind with the message, “Go Deeper.” Once more he went in, this time even deeper, and what else would he find but a diamond mine! The humble woodcutter was overwhelmed and realized immediately that all of these gifts had come from the grace of the sage. The story is told to illustrate that our inner resources are waiting to come to our aid, to offer us fulfillment, we simply need to take the time to “go deeper,” to access them. Nonviolence can be that voice inside, reminding us in every situation to go deeper and find more resources for courage and compassion than we knew we had, enabling us to claim our true wealth as human beings. &#160; Experiment in Nonviolence: Take the time today to practice “going deeper” and see what inner resource you hit upon. &#160; Daily Metta 2015, a service of the Metta Center for Nonviolence, is a daily reflection on the strategic and spiritual insights of Mahatma Gandhi in thought, word and deed. As Gandhi called his life an “experiment in truth,” we have included an experiment in nonviolence to accompany each Daily Metta. Check in every day for new inspiration. Each year will be dedicated to another wisdom teacher.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/go-deeper-woodcutter-daily-metta/">&#8220;Go Deeper, Woodcutter&#8221;&#8211;Daily Metta</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org">Metta Center</a>.</p>
]]></summary>
		<content type="html" xml:base="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/go-deeper-woodcutter-daily-metta/"><![CDATA[<h1>June 12:</h1>
<h2><a href="http://mettacenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/gandhi-21.png"><img class=" size-medium wp-image-15863 alignright" src="http://mettacenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/gandhi-21-300x224.png" alt="gandhi-21" width="300" height="224" /></a>&#8220;I am but a seeker after Truth.&#8221;</h2>
<p><em>&#8211;Gandhi (Young India, June 17, 1926) </em></p>
<p>Hindu mystic, father of the modern Vedantic movement, Sri Ramakrishna of Dakshineswar, often shared stories with his devotees to illustrate principles important for understanding the nature of Reality, what Gandhi would call, Sat, or Truth with a capital T. The story of the woodcutter and the sage is one of my favorites:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">There once lived a poor woodcutter. He could not earn a decent living because the trees available to him were not of a very good quality. A sage lived in that forest, and each day would sit under a banyan tree. One day, the woodcutter approached the sage, almost in desperation, and the sage looked at him. The woodcutter peered deeply into his eyes, which seemed to say to him “Go Deeper.” The woodcutter decided he would do just that, and he moved more deeply into the forest and came across sandalwood trees. These trees were very sought after, and the woodcutter only had to work once a week. But he thought about the sage again, and the words would not leave him, “Go Deeper.” So he decided to venture even deeper into the forest, and lo&#8217; and behold, he came across a silver mine! Amazing he thought! His worries were truly over. And some time passed, but again, the sage’s eyes came to his mind with the message, “Go Deeper.” Once more he went in, this time even deeper, and what else would he find but a diamond mine! The humble woodcutter was overwhelmed and realized immediately that all of these gifts had come from the grace of the sage.</p>
<p>The story is told to illustrate that our inner resources are waiting to come to our aid, to offer us fulfillment, we simply need to take the time to “go deeper,” to access them. Nonviolence can be that voice inside, reminding us in every situation to go deeper and find more resources for courage and compassion than we knew we had, enabling us to claim our true wealth as human beings.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Experiment in Nonviolence:</strong><br />
Take the time today to practice “going deeper” and see what inner resource you hit upon.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong><a href="http://mettacenter.us8.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=768c54dd5fa713b52b1623e91&amp;id=89e9ef9bef"><img class="alignleft  wp-image-15375" src="http://mettacenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Daily-Metta-250x250.png" alt="Daily Metta 250x250" width="115" height="115" /></a>Daily Metta 2015, a service of the Metta Center for Nonviolence, is a daily reflection on the strategic and spiritual insights of Mahatma Gandhi in thought, word and deed. As Gandhi called his life an “experiment in truth,” we have included an experiment in nonviolence to accompany each Daily Metta. Check in every day for new inspiration. Each year will be dedicated to another wisdom teacher.</strong></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/go-deeper-woodcutter-daily-metta/">&#8220;Go Deeper, Woodcutter&#8221;&#8211;Daily Metta</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org">Metta Center</a>.</p>
]]></content>
			<link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/go-deeper-woodcutter-daily-metta/#comments" thr:count="0"/>
		<link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/go-deeper-woodcutter-daily-metta/feed/atom/" thr:count="0"/>
		<thr:total>0</thr:total>
	</entry>
		<entry>
		<author>
			<name>Stephanie Van Hook</name>
					</author>
		<title type="html"><![CDATA[&#8220;In my country&#8221;&#8211;Daily Metta]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/in-my-country-daily-metta/" />
		<id>http://mettacenter.org/?p=16769</id>
		<updated>2015-06-10T18:08:38Z</updated>
		<published>2015-06-11T08:00:22Z</published>
		<category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="Daily Metta" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="ann peacock" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="gandhi" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="in my country" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="juliette binoche" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="Nonviolence" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="samuel l jackson" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="truth and reconciliation commission" />		<summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>June 11: “ My faith in truth and nonviolence is ever growing.” &#8211;Gandhi (Harijan, May 1, 1937) In 2005 I lived in the West African country of Benin as a volunteer with the Peace Corps. I had access to a small video screen to watch films from time to time, and in care packages from my parents, I would often find a new video. One film they sent me essentially changed the course of my life forever. In My Country was a Hollywood-esque film, made for the American public in particular, starring the likes of Samuel L. Jackson and Juliette Binoche. It was the story of Antje Krog, South African writer who followed and reported on the Truth and Reconciliation Commission, a form of restorative, transitional justice, in the post-apartheid transition to democracy. I was riveted by it, and decided to watch interviews of those who made the film, and this is where the seed was really planted in me to learn nonviolence more systematically. I will never forget when the screen-writer, Ann Peacock, a passionate, talented woman in the middle of her life, looks at the interviewer and states emphatically, and matter-of-factly, even nobly: I wrote this story so that people would know that the Truth and Reconciliation Commission existed. What a simple statement, and a humble task: using film media to tell a story that would otherwise be forgotten, discarded, or worse, seen as irrelevant. And what a form of activism: she did not do this be famous, to make “a name” for herself in the film industry, and I was struck by her honesty, her vision of what a human being can do in life with the talents we have. She was driven by the spirit of showing people that there is another way to do things, one that has been done before, and that we can improve on past experiments. What a great service, and something we are all capable of doing. &#160; Experiment in Nonviolence: If you could show people one aspect of nonviolence, of “another way” out of violence, what it be? Think of a way of doing it based on the talents you have cultivated. &#160; Daily Metta 2015, a service of the Metta Center for Nonviolence, is a daily reflection on the strategic and spiritual insights of Mahatma Gandhi in thought, word and deed. As Gandhi called his life an “experiment in truth,” we have included an experiment in nonviolence to accompany each Daily Metta. Check in every day for new inspiration. Each year will be dedicated to another wisdom teacher.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/in-my-country-daily-metta/">&#8220;In my country&#8221;&#8211;Daily Metta</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org">Metta Center</a>.</p>
]]></summary>
		<content type="html" xml:base="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/in-my-country-daily-metta/"><![CDATA[<h1>June 11:</h1>
<h2>
<a href="http://mettacenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/gandhi-21.png"><img class=" size-medium wp-image-15863 alignright" src="http://mettacenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/gandhi-21-300x224.png" alt="gandhi-21" width="300" height="224" /></a>“ My faith in truth and nonviolence is ever growing.”</h2>
<p><em>&#8211;Gandhi (Harijan, May 1, 1937)</em></p>
<p>In 2005 I lived in the West African country of Benin as a volunteer with the Peace Corps. I had access to a small video screen to watch films from time to time, and in care packages from my parents, I would often find a new video. One film they sent me essentially changed the course of my life forever. <em>In My Country</em> was a Hollywood-esque film, made for the American public in particular, starring the likes of Samuel L. Jackson and Juliette Binoche. It was the story of Antje Krog, South African writer who followed and reported on the Truth and Reconciliation Commission, a form of restorative, transitional justice, in the post-apartheid transition to democracy. I was riveted by it, and decided to watch interviews of those who made the film, and this is where the seed was really planted in me to learn nonviolence more systematically. I will never forget when the screen-writer, Ann Peacock, a passionate, talented woman in the middle of her life, looks at the interviewer and states emphatically, and matter-of-factly, even nobly:<em> I wrote this story so that people would know that the Truth and Reconciliation Commission existed.</em> What a simple statement, and a humble task: using film media to tell a story that would otherwise be forgotten, discarded, or worse, seen as irrelevant. And what a form of activism: she did not do this be famous, to make “a name” for herself in the film industry, and I was struck by her honesty, her vision of what a human being can do in life with the talents we have. She was driven by the spirit of showing people that there is another way to do things, one that has been done before, and that we can improve on past experiments. What a great service, and something we are all capable of doing.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Experiment in Nonviolence:</strong><br />
If you could show people one aspect of nonviolence, of “another way” out of violence, what it be? Think of a way of doing it based on the talents you have cultivated.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong><a href="http://mettacenter.us8.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=768c54dd5fa713b52b1623e91&amp;id=89e9ef9bef"><img class="alignleft  wp-image-15375" src="http://mettacenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Daily-Metta-250x250.png" alt="Daily Metta 250x250" width="115" height="115" /></a>Daily Metta 2015, a service of the Metta Center for Nonviolence, is a daily reflection on the strategic and spiritual insights of Mahatma Gandhi in thought, word and deed. As Gandhi called his life an “experiment in truth,” we have included an experiment in nonviolence to accompany each Daily Metta. Check in every day for new inspiration. Each year will be dedicated to another wisdom teacher.</strong></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/in-my-country-daily-metta/">&#8220;In my country&#8221;&#8211;Daily Metta</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org">Metta Center</a>.</p>
]]></content>
			<link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/in-my-country-daily-metta/#comments" thr:count="0"/>
		<link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/in-my-country-daily-metta/feed/atom/" thr:count="0"/>
		<thr:total>0</thr:total>
	</entry>
		<entry>
		<author>
			<name>Stephanie Van Hook</name>
					</author>
		<title type="html"><![CDATA[&#8220;I am because you are&#8221;&#8211;Daily Metta]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/i-am-because-you-are-daily-metta/" />
		<id>http://mettacenter.org/?p=16728</id>
		<updated>2015-06-10T01:48:42Z</updated>
		<published>2015-06-10T01:48:42Z</published>
		<category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="Daily Metta" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="desmond tutu" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="gandhi" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="Nonviolence" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="ubuntu" />		<summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>June 10: “I believe in the essential unity of humanity, and for that matter, all that lives.” &#8211;Gandhi (Young India, September 3, 1925) In order to make nonviolent institutions possible, they have to be built on a solid cultural foundation that embodies respect and even reverence for the human experience. Not a reverence with our mouths only, but a deep awareness of our true dignity and relationship to all of life. We need to lift up the best parts of ourselves and let them guide us. So, being human: Does that mean being a consumer, destined to war at all levels, an automaton in front of a screen, “entertaining ourselves to death”? Or can we find and agree on a more inspiring, more realistic conception? The Nguni Bantu linguistic family, in the region of South Africa, has a very workable term for this concept: ubuntu (sounds like “oo-boon-too”). It’s literal translation is most closely related to terms such as “human-ness” and “human-kindness,” though as it has become popularized, mainly by South African peacemaker Desmond Tutu, it has come to mean that we only express our humanness through other human beings, or in short, “I am because you are.” My dignity comes from the dignity of others, and my recognition of their dignity. My well-being is caught up in the web of life all around me. Conversely, when I dehumanize another, I dehumanize myself. By my very nature of being human, I cannot escape this interconnection. I can only learn how to recognize it faster, at ever-deepening levels, and harness it to guide me into “right action” to use a Buddhist term. But is that recognition, whether on an individual or massive scale, not one of the greatest victories possible for us? &#160; Experiment in Nonviolence: Reflect on the concept of ubuntu and find one way to express it consciously in your actions today. &#160; Daily Metta 2015, a service of the Metta Center for Nonviolence, is a daily reflection on the strategic and spiritual insights of Mahatma Gandhi in thought, word and deed. As Gandhi called his life an “experiment in truth,” we have included an experiment in nonviolence to accompany each Daily Metta. Check in every day for new inspiration. Each year will be dedicated to another wisdom teacher.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/i-am-because-you-are-daily-metta/">&#8220;I am because you are&#8221;&#8211;Daily Metta</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org">Metta Center</a>.</p>
]]></summary>
		<content type="html" xml:base="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/i-am-because-you-are-daily-metta/"><![CDATA[<h1><b>June 10: </b></h1>
<h2><b><a href="http://mettacenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/gandhi-21.png"><img class=" size-medium wp-image-15863 alignright" src="http://mettacenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/gandhi-21-300x224.png" alt="gandhi-21" width="300" height="224" /></a>“I believe in the essential unity of humanity, and for that matter, all that lives.” </b></h2>
<p><i>&#8211;Gandhi (Young India, September 3, 1925) </i></p>
<p>In order to make nonviolent institutions possible, they have to be built on a solid cultural foundation that embodies respect and even reverence for the human experience. Not a reverence with our mouths only, but a deep awareness of our true dignity and relationship to all of life. We need to lift up the best parts of ourselves and let them guide us. So, being human: Does that mean being a consumer, destined to war at all levels, an automaton in front of a screen, “entertaining ourselves to death”? Or can we find and agree on a more inspiring, more realistic conception?</p>
<p>The Nguni Bantu linguistic family, in the region of South Africa, has a very workable term for this concept: <i>ubuntu (</i>sounds like “oo-boon-too”). It’s literal translation is most closely related to terms such as “human-ness” and “human-kindness,” though as it has become popularized, mainly by South African peacemaker Desmond Tutu, it has come to mean that we only express our humanness through other human beings, or in short, “I am because you are.” My dignity comes from the dignity of others, and my recognition of their dignity. My well-being is caught up in the web of life all around me. Conversely, when I dehumanize another, I dehumanize myself. By my very nature of being human, I cannot escape this interconnection. I can only learn how to recognize it faster, at ever-deepening levels, and harness it to guide me into “right action” to use a Buddhist term. But is that recognition, whether on an individual or massive scale, not one of the greatest victories possible for us?</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Experiment in Nonviolence: </b></p>
<p>Reflect on the concept of ubuntu and find one way to express it consciously in your actions today.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong><a href="http://mettacenter.us8.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=768c54dd5fa713b52b1623e91&amp;id=89e9ef9bef"><img class="alignleft  wp-image-15375" src="http://mettacenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Daily-Metta-250x250.png" alt="Daily Metta 250x250" width="115" height="115" /></a>Daily Metta 2015, a service of the Metta Center for Nonviolence, is a daily reflection on the strategic and spiritual insights of Mahatma Gandhi in thought, word and deed. As Gandhi called his life an “experiment in truth,” we have included an experiment in nonviolence to accompany each Daily Metta. Check in every day for new inspiration. Each year will be dedicated to another wisdom teacher.</strong></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/i-am-because-you-are-daily-metta/">&#8220;I am because you are&#8221;&#8211;Daily Metta</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org">Metta Center</a>.</p>
]]></content>
			<link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/i-am-because-you-are-daily-metta/#comments" thr:count="0"/>
		<link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/i-am-because-you-are-daily-metta/feed/atom/" thr:count="0"/>
		<thr:total>0</thr:total>
	</entry>
		<entry>
		<author>
			<name>Stephanie Van Hook</name>
					</author>
		<title type="html"><![CDATA[&#8220;Walk Alone&#8221;&#8211;Daily Metta]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/walk-alone-daily-metta/" />
		<id>http://mettacenter.org/?p=16716</id>
		<updated>2015-06-09T15:17:21Z</updated>
		<published>2015-06-09T15:17:21Z</published>
		<category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="Daily Metta" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="ekla chalo re" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="gandhi" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="Nonviolence" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="rabindranath tagore" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="songs" />		<summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>June 9 “There are moments in your life when you must act, even though you cannot carry your best friends with you.” &#8211;Gandhi (The Monthly Review, Calcutta, October, 1941) One of Gandhi’s favorite songs was Ekla Chalo Re, a Bengali hymn translated as “Walk Alone.” Written by the famous Rabindranath Tagore, the lyrics are as follows, translated by Tagore himself from Bengali: If they answer not to your call walk alone If they are afraid and cower mutely facing the wall, O thou unlucky one, open your mind and speak out alone. If they turn away, and desert you when crossing the wilderness, O thou unlucky one, trample the thorns under thy tread, and along the blood-lined track travel alone. If they shut doors and do not hold up the light when the night is troubled with storm, O thou unlucky one, with the thunder flame of pain ignite your own heart, and let it burn alone. Gandhi is known to have drawn from the power within this song, singing it as he traveled alone into violence-rife villages toward the end of his life, in an effort to get the bloodshed  between Hindus and Muslims to cease. &#160; Experiment in Nonviolence: Learn the words of Ekla Chalo Re by heart, as Gandhi did; or at least let’s take them to heart. &#160; &#160; Daily Metta 2015, a service of the Metta Center for Nonviolence, is a daily reflection on the strategic and spiritual insights of Mahatma Gandhi in thought, word and deed. As Gandhi called his life an “experiment in truth,” we have included an experiment in nonviolence to accompany each Daily Metta. Check in every day for new inspiration. Each year will be dedicated to another wisdom teacher.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/walk-alone-daily-metta/">&#8220;Walk Alone&#8221;&#8211;Daily Metta</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org">Metta Center</a>.</p>
]]></summary>
		<content type="html" xml:base="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/walk-alone-daily-metta/"><![CDATA[<h1>June 9</h1>
<h2><b><a href="http://mettacenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/gandhi-21.png"><img class=" size-medium wp-image-15863 alignright" src="http://mettacenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/gandhi-21-300x224.png" alt="gandhi-21" width="300" height="224" /></a>“There are moments in your life when you must act, even though you cannot carry your best friends with you.” </b></h2>
<p><i>&#8211;Gandhi (The Monthly Review, Calcutta, October, 1941) </i></p>
<p>One of Gandhi’s favorite songs was <i>Ekla Chalo Re</i>, a Bengali hymn translated as “Walk Alone.” Written by the famous Rabindranath Tagore, the lyrics are as follows, translated by Tagore himself from Bengali:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">If they answer not to your call walk alone</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">If they are afraid and cower mutely facing the wall,</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">O thou unlucky one,</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">open your mind and speak out alone.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">If they turn away, and desert you when crossing the wilderness,</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">O thou unlucky one,</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">trample the thorns under thy tread,</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">and along the blood-lined track travel alone.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">If they shut doors and do not hold up the light when the night is troubled with storm,</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">O thou unlucky one,</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">with the thunder flame of pain ignite your own heart,</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">and let it burn alone.</p>
<p>Gandhi is known to have drawn from the power within this song, singing it as he traveled alone into violence-rife villages toward the end of his life, in an effort to get the bloodshed  between Hindus and Muslims to cease.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Experiment in Nonviolence: </b></p>
<p>Learn the words of <i>Ekla Chalo Re</i> by heart, as Gandhi did; or at least let’s <i>take</i> them to heart.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/j64PR78bB4I" width="560" height="315" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong><a href="http://mettacenter.us8.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=768c54dd5fa713b52b1623e91&amp;id=89e9ef9bef"><img class="alignleft  wp-image-15375" src="http://mettacenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Daily-Metta-250x250.png" alt="Daily Metta 250x250" width="115" height="115" /></a>Daily Metta 2015, a service of the Metta Center for Nonviolence, is a daily reflection on the strategic and spiritual insights of Mahatma Gandhi in thought, word and deed. As Gandhi called his life an “experiment in truth,” we have included an experiment in nonviolence to accompany each Daily Metta. Check in every day for new inspiration. Each year will be dedicated to another wisdom teacher.</strong></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/walk-alone-daily-metta/">&#8220;Walk Alone&#8221;&#8211;Daily Metta</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org">Metta Center</a>.</p>
]]></content>
			<link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/walk-alone-daily-metta/#comments" thr:count="0"/>
		<link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/walk-alone-daily-metta/feed/atom/" thr:count="0"/>
		<thr:total>0</thr:total>
	</entry>
		<entry>
		<author>
			<name>Stephanie Van Hook</name>
					</author>
		<title type="html"><![CDATA[&#8220;Silent Mondays&#8221;&#8211;Daily Metta]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/silent-mondays-daily-metta/" />
		<id>http://mettacenter.org/?p=16711</id>
		<updated>2015-06-08T18:48:39Z</updated>
		<published>2015-06-08T18:45:42Z</published>
		<category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="Daily Metta" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="daily metta" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="gandhi" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="Nonviolence" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="silent mondays" />		<summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>June 8: “It has often occurred to me that a seeker after truth has to be silent.” &#8211;Gandhi (Young India, August 6, 1925) In the language of pop psychology, some might say that Gandhi was an introvert as a child and a young man. He experienced a high level of social anxiety and was generally categorized as shy and timid, (though, such words reveal little about his interior life). When he began his lifelong work in the Indian freedom struggle, however, he transformed his introversion and “shyness” into something that helped, instead of hindered, him: a temporary vow of silence, every Monday, without fail. Besides giving him a chance to “relieve pressure” (his words),  he soon realized that a person of few words will have to choose their words carefully, which is a great aid to conscious speech, or “nonviolence in word.”  And in fact, Nehru later will testify that “Gandhi never wrote or said a word he did not mean.” Whether the struggle was intense or a visitor arrived who could only be there that one day, Gandhi kept his vow of silence. He did have a few very compassionate exceptions, in his own words, “When I took the vow of silent Mondays, I allowed myself two exceptions. I decided that in a moment of unendurable physical pain, or to comfort someone in equal mental pain, I would break my silence and say what was necessary.” Experiment in Nonviolence: Find a time each week&#8211;it does not have to be an entire day&#8211;to practice the discipline of silence. Work a bit of silence into each day. If you already do that, consider a conscious exploration of your word to silence ratio each day. Can you incorporate more silence on the one hand, and more power into your chosen speech, on the other? &#160; &#160; Daily Metta 2015, a service of the Metta Center for Nonviolence, is a daily reflection on the strategic and spiritual insights of Mahatma Gandhi in thought, word and deed. As Gandhi called his life an “experiment in truth,” we have included an experiment in nonviolence to accompany each Daily Metta. Check in every day for new inspiration. Each year will be dedicated to another wisdom teacher.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/silent-mondays-daily-metta/">&#8220;Silent Mondays&#8221;&#8211;Daily Metta</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org">Metta Center</a>.</p>
]]></summary>
		<content type="html" xml:base="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/silent-mondays-daily-metta/"><![CDATA[<h1><b>June 8: </b></h1>
<h2><b><a href="http://mettacenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/gandhi-21.png"><img class=" size-medium wp-image-15863 alignright" src="http://mettacenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/gandhi-21-300x224.png" alt="gandhi-21" width="300" height="224" /></a>“It has often occurred to me that a seeker after truth has to be silent.” </b></h2>
<p><i>&#8211;Gandhi (Young India, August 6, 1925) </i></p>
<p>In the language of pop psychology, some might say that Gandhi was an introvert as a child and a young man. He experienced a high level of social anxiety and was generally categorized as shy and timid, (though, such words reveal little about his interior life). When he began his lifelong work in the Indian freedom struggle, however, he transformed his introversion and “shyness” into something that helped, instead of hindered, him: a temporary vow of silence, every Monday, without fail. Besides giving him a chance to “relieve pressure” (his words),  he soon realized that a person of few words will have to choose their words carefully, which is a great aid to conscious speech, or “nonviolence in word.”  And in fact, Nehru later will testify that “Gandhi never wrote or said a word he did not mean.”</p>
<p>Whether the struggle was intense or a visitor arrived who could only be there that one day, Gandhi kept his vow of silence. He did have a few very compassionate exceptions, in his own words, “When I took the vow of silent Mondays, I allowed myself two exceptions. I decided that in a moment of unendurable physical pain, or to comfort someone in equal mental pain, I would break my silence and say what was necessary.”</p>
<p><b>Experiment in Nonviolence:</b></p>
<p>Find a time each week&#8211;it does not have to be an entire day&#8211;to practice the discipline of silence. Work a bit of silence into each day. If you already do that, consider a conscious exploration of your word to silence ratio each day. Can you incorporate more silence on the one hand, and more power into your chosen speech, on the other?</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong><a href="http://mettacenter.us8.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=768c54dd5fa713b52b1623e91&amp;id=89e9ef9bef"><img class="alignleft  wp-image-15375" src="http://mettacenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Daily-Metta-250x250.png" alt="Daily Metta 250x250" width="115" height="115" /></a>Daily Metta 2015, a service of the Metta Center for Nonviolence, is a daily reflection on the strategic and spiritual insights of Mahatma Gandhi in thought, word and deed. As Gandhi called his life an “experiment in truth,” we have included an experiment in nonviolence to accompany each Daily Metta. Check in every day for new inspiration. Each year will be dedicated to another wisdom teacher.</strong></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/silent-mondays-daily-metta/">&#8220;Silent Mondays&#8221;&#8211;Daily Metta</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org">Metta Center</a>.</p>
]]></content>
			<link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/silent-mondays-daily-metta/#comments" thr:count="0"/>
		<link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/silent-mondays-daily-metta/feed/atom/" thr:count="0"/>
		<thr:total>0</thr:total>
	</entry>
		<entry>
		<author>
			<name>Stephanie Van Hook</name>
					</author>
		<title type="html"><![CDATA[&#8220;Hungry for Nonviolence&#8221;&#8211;Daily Metta]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/hungry-for-nonviolence/" />
		<id>http://mettacenter.org/?p=16704</id>
		<updated>2015-06-08T02:03:01Z</updated>
		<published>2015-06-08T01:50:35Z</published>
		<category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="Daily Metta" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="daily metta" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="food" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="gandhi" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="kaka kelelkar" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="Nonviolence" />		<summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>June 7: “My love for nonviolence is superior to every other thing mundane or supramundane.” &#8211;Gandhi (Young India, February 20, 1930)   &#160; Gandhi loved nonviolence more than anything else, including food. That’s right, foodies, we do not have any photos taken by him of, say, his neem chutney or simple rice and dhal.  His experiments with his diet were on-going throughout his entire life, and often came to his advantage when, for example, he would be in prison for civil disobedience. No salt today? No problem. No tea for prisoners? No sweat. So, what would you do if Gandhi were at your house for dinner? Wouldn’t you want to be hospitable, serve him something wholesome, tasty and delicious? Of course. It’s natural. Here’s a story to consider, though: One time, he was visiting a home in Bengal, and was experimenting in an effort to better understand the body, with a fruit-only diet. The hosts, with the best of intentions, found fruits of all varieties, dried and fresh, and also took the time to cook a variety of fruit dishes for him to relish. They spread the banquet before Gandhiji, who became very embarrassed. According to Kaka Kalelkar, who was with him, he stated that he was in search of simplicity, and that the spread was more than unnecessary for him. At that moment, he decided that he would limit his diet to only five natural ingredients a day, and on top of this, to eat before sunset! Kalelkar recalls that this was a great difficulty for those around the Mahatma, as they would have to debate with him regularly about whether he saw differences between lemons and oranges or if adding some sweetener to his food would count as a one of the foods for the day, and they had to remember what he ate at the previous meal to ensure that he would get a balanced diet. Sounds extravagant, in some ways, and in others, it makes perfect sense. All of life was an experiment, for him, and this one was about giving the body just what it needed &#8212; not what it craved! So, remember when Barack Obama told school children that if he could dine with anyone, it would be Mahatma Gandhi? You might want to think twice before agreeing&#8211;unless you were willing to go against the cravings of the palate&#8211;no savoring&#8211;and spend the rest of the time discussing nonviolent strategy. Talk about soul-food! &#160; Experiment in Nonviolence: Is there something that you eat that you know is bad for you? Try to replace it with something more wholesome the next time you have a craving. &#160; &#160; Daily Metta 2015, a service of the Metta Center for Nonviolence, is a daily reflection on the strategic and spiritual insights of Mahatma Gandhi in thought, word and deed. As Gandhi called his life an “experiment in truth,” we have included an experiment in nonviolence to accompany each Daily Metta. Check in every day for new inspiration. Each [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/hungry-for-nonviolence/">&#8220;Hungry for Nonviolence&#8221;&#8211;Daily Metta</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org">Metta Center</a>.</p>
]]></summary>
		<content type="html" xml:base="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/hungry-for-nonviolence/"><![CDATA[<h1><b>June 7: </b></h1>
<h2><b><a href="http://mettacenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/gandhi-21.png"><img class=" size-medium wp-image-15863 alignright" src="http://mettacenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/gandhi-21-300x224.png" alt="gandhi-21" width="300" height="224" /></a>“My love for nonviolence is superior to every other thing mundane or supramundane.” </b></h2>
<p><i>&#8211;Gandhi (Young India, February 20, 1930) </i><b> </b></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Gandhi loved nonviolence more than anything else, including food. That’s right, foodies, we do not have any photos taken by him of, say, his neem chutney or simple rice and dhal.  His experiments with his diet were on-going throughout his entire life, and often came to his advantage when, for example, he would be in prison for civil disobedience. <i>No salt today? No problem. No tea for prisoners? No sweat. </i></p>
<p>So, what would you do if Gandhi were at your house for dinner? Wouldn’t you want to be hospitable, serve him something wholesome, tasty and delicious? Of course. It’s natural. Here’s a story to consider, though:</p>
<p>One time, he was visiting a home in Bengal, and was experimenting in an effort to better understand the body, with a fruit-only diet. The hosts, with the best of intentions, found fruits of all varieties, dried and fresh, and also took the time to cook a variety of fruit dishes for him to relish. They spread the banquet before Gandhiji, who became very embarrassed. According to Kaka Kalelkar, who was with him, he stated that he was in search of simplicity, and that the spread was more than unnecessary for him. At that moment, he decided that he would limit his diet to only five natural ingredients a day, and on top of this, to eat before sunset! Kalelkar recalls that this was a great difficulty for those around the Mahatma, as they would have to debate with him regularly about whether he saw differences between lemons and oranges or if adding some sweetener to his food would count as a one of the foods for the day, and they had to remember what he ate at the previous meal to ensure that he would get a balanced diet. Sounds extravagant, in some ways, and in others, it makes perfect sense. All of life was an experiment, for him, and this one was about giving the body just what it needed &#8212; not what it craved!</p>
<p>So, remember when <a href="http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/world/us/Obama-says-he-would-like-to-have-dinner-with-Mahatma-Gandhi/articleshow/4988799.cms">Barack Obama told school children </a>that if he could dine with anyone, it would be Mahatma Gandhi? You might want to think twice before agreeing&#8211;unless you were willing to go against the cravings of the palate&#8211;no savoring&#8211;and spend the rest of the time discussing nonviolent strategy. Talk about soul-food!</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Experiment in Nonviolence: </b></p>
<p>Is there something that you eat that you know is bad for you? Try to replace it with something more wholesome the next time you have a craving.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong><a href="http://mettacenter.us8.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=768c54dd5fa713b52b1623e91&amp;id=89e9ef9bef"><img class="alignleft  wp-image-15375" src="http://mettacenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Daily-Metta-250x250.png" alt="Daily Metta 250x250" width="115" height="115" /></a>Daily Metta 2015, a service of the Metta Center for Nonviolence, is a daily reflection on the strategic and spiritual insights of Mahatma Gandhi in thought, word and deed. As Gandhi called his life an “experiment in truth,” we have included an experiment in nonviolence to accompany each Daily Metta. Check in every day for new inspiration. Each year will be dedicated to another wisdom teacher.</strong></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/hungry-for-nonviolence/">&#8220;Hungry for Nonviolence&#8221;&#8211;Daily Metta</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org">Metta Center</a>.</p>
]]></content>
			<link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/hungry-for-nonviolence/#comments" thr:count="0"/>
		<link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/hungry-for-nonviolence/feed/atom/" thr:count="0"/>
		<thr:total>0</thr:total>
	</entry>
		<entry>
		<author>
			<name>Stephanie Van Hook</name>
					</author>
		<title type="html"><![CDATA[&#8220;Nonviolence is not easy&#8221;&#8211;Daily Metta]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/nonviolence-is-not-easy-daily-metta/" />
		<id>http://mettacenter.org/?p=16701</id>
		<updated>2015-06-07T00:08:22Z</updated>
		<published>2015-06-07T00:08:22Z</published>
		<category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="Daily Metta" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="bernard lafayette" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="daily metta" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="gandhi" />		<summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>June 6: “Nonviolence is not an easy thing to understand, still less to practice.” &#8211;Gandhi (Young India, February 7, 1929) If you are practicing nonviolence and finding it difficult, congratulations, you are doing something right! Nonviolence is challenging because it requires so much more of us than passivity or violence. When you have a gun in your hand, you don’t have to think about another way, you use it. But when you have nonviolence, you have creativity, intelligence and compassion, and you are asked to draw upon all of these in search of your solution. It makes us wiser, not to mention, the economy of it! As the great Dr. Bernard Lafayette said, “With nonviolence, as soon as you step out of the shower, you have everything you need.” While nonviolence is as “old as the hills” as Gandhi noted, that it can be studied, developed and strategically applied is a relatively new concept in the history of human achievement. This is why the Metta Center for Nonviolence is dedicated to this one task&#8211; fleshing out, understanding, the dynamics of nonviolence so that all who wish to join this great experiment can do so more safely and more effectively. &#160; Experiment in Nonviolence: Nonviolence is hard, ceaseless and important work, so be sure to give yourself some time for a nap, even five minutes, say instead of checking email, watching TV or scrolling on social media. &#160; Daily Metta 2015, a service of the Metta Center for Nonviolence, is a daily reflection on the strategic and spiritual insights of Mahatma Gandhi in thought, word and deed. As Gandhi called his life an “experiment in truth,” we have included an experiment in nonviolence to accompany each Daily Metta. Check in every day for new inspiration. Each year will be dedicated to another wisdom teacher.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/nonviolence-is-not-easy-daily-metta/">&#8220;Nonviolence is not easy&#8221;&#8211;Daily Metta</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org">Metta Center</a>.</p>
]]></summary>
		<content type="html" xml:base="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/nonviolence-is-not-easy-daily-metta/"><![CDATA[<h1><b>June 6: </b></h1>
<h2><b><a href="http://mettacenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/gandhi-21.png"><img class=" size-medium wp-image-15863 alignright" src="http://mettacenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/gandhi-21-300x224.png" alt="gandhi-21" width="300" height="224" /></a>“Nonviolence is not an easy thing to understand, still less to practice.” </b></h2>
<p><i>&#8211;Gandhi (Young India, February 7, 1929) </i></p>
<p>If you are practicing nonviolence and finding it difficult, congratulations, you are doing something right! Nonviolence <i>is </i>challenging because it requires so much more of us than passivity or violence. When you have a gun in your hand, you don’t have to think about another way, you use it. But when you have nonviolence, you have creativity, intelligence and compassion, and you are asked to draw upon all of these in search of your solution. It makes us wiser, not to mention, the economy of it! As the great Dr. Bernard Lafayette said, <em>“With nonviolence, as soon as you step out of the shower, you have everything you need.”</em></p>
<p>While nonviolence is as “old as the hills” as Gandhi noted, that it can be studied, developed and strategically applied is a relatively new concept in the history of human achievement. This is why the Metta Center for Nonviolence is dedicated to this one task&#8211; fleshing out, understanding, the dynamics of nonviolence so that all who wish to join this great experiment can do so more safely and more effectively.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Experiment in Nonviolence: </b></p>
<p>Nonviolence is hard, ceaseless and important work, so be sure to give yourself some time for a nap, even five minutes, say instead of checking email, watching TV or scrolling on social media.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong><a href="http://mettacenter.us8.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=768c54dd5fa713b52b1623e91&amp;id=89e9ef9bef"><img class="alignleft  wp-image-15375" src="http://mettacenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Daily-Metta-250x250.png" alt="Daily Metta 250x250" width="115" height="115" /></a>Daily Metta 2015, a service of the Metta Center for Nonviolence, is a daily reflection on the strategic and spiritual insights of Mahatma Gandhi in thought, word and deed. As Gandhi called his life an “experiment in truth,” we have included an experiment in nonviolence to accompany each Daily Metta. Check in every day for new inspiration. Each year will be dedicated to another wisdom teacher.</strong></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/nonviolence-is-not-easy-daily-metta/">&#8220;Nonviolence is not easy&#8221;&#8211;Daily Metta</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org">Metta Center</a>.</p>
]]></content>
			<link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/nonviolence-is-not-easy-daily-metta/#comments" thr:count="0"/>
		<link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/nonviolence-is-not-easy-daily-metta/feed/atom/" thr:count="0"/>
		<thr:total>0</thr:total>
	</entry>
		<entry>
		<author>
			<name>Stephanie Van Hook</name>
					</author>
		<title type="html"><![CDATA[&#8220;Who&#8217;s afraid of Gandhi?&#8221;&#8211;Daily Metta]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/whos-afraid-of-mahatma-gandhi-daily-metta/" />
		<id>http://mettacenter.org/?p=16697</id>
		<updated>2015-06-05T23:58:29Z</updated>
		<published>2015-06-05T23:56:02Z</published>
		<category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="Daily Metta" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="daily metta" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="gandhi" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="Nonviolence" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="threat" />		<summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>June 5: “It is not so much the British guns that are responsible for our subjugation as our voluntary co-operation.” &#8211;Gandhi (Young India, February 9, 1921) &#160; There comes a point when our common understanding of conflict is insufficient and we need to reach deeper.  And this is not always easy, for we just may see our own responsibility staring us in the face.  But what a relief, really, to break out of the spell cast over us when we feel threatened: all our attention goes to the other: “They are doing it to us: get rid of them.&#8221;  But this is so disempowering, for the flip side of that spell is “we have no agency, we are helpless.”  Everyone likes to be guiltless, but no one likes to be helpless. Beginning in 1909 with his classic tract, Hind Swaraj Gandhi argued “The British did not take India; we gave her to them.”  What a wake-up call!  And he, of course, carried it out on a gigantic scale, as the double Nobel-Prize winner, Albert Szent-Gyeorgyi astutely observed: “Gandhi taught the world that there are higher things than force, higher even than life itself; he proved that force had lost its suggestive power.” Or rather, in our vocabulary, threat power had lost its suggestive force. No conflict can be resolved if both parties are in an “us-vs.-them” mindframe; it behoves the nonviolent party to step out of that frame and own our own responsibility &#8212; and power. &#160; Experiment in nonviolence: Try this out on our own scale: the next time we feel we’re being threatened or held down, ask, &#8220;are we perhaps overlooking our own power here?&#8221; &#160; Daily Metta 2015, a service of the Metta Center for Nonviolence, is a daily reflection on the strategic and spiritual insights of Mahatma Gandhi in thought, word and deed. As Gandhi called his life an “experiment in truth,” we have included an experiment in nonviolence to accompany each Daily Metta. Check in every day for new inspiration. Each year will be dedicated to another wisdom teacher. &#160; &#160;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/whos-afraid-of-mahatma-gandhi-daily-metta/">&#8220;Who&#8217;s afraid of Gandhi?&#8221;&#8211;Daily Metta</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org">Metta Center</a>.</p>
]]></summary>
		<content type="html" xml:base="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/whos-afraid-of-mahatma-gandhi-daily-metta/"><![CDATA[<h1><b>June 5: </b></h1>
<h2><b><a href="http://mettacenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/gandhi-21.png"><img class=" size-medium wp-image-15863 alignright" src="http://mettacenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/gandhi-21-300x224.png" alt="gandhi-21" width="300" height="224" /></a>“It is not so much the British guns that are responsible for our subjugation as our </b><b>voluntary co-operation.” </b></h2>
<p><i>&#8211;Gandhi (Young India, February 9, 1921) </i></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>There comes a point when our common understanding of conflict is insufficient and we need to reach deeper.  And this is not always easy, for we just may see our own responsibility staring us in the face.  But what a relief, really, to break out of the spell cast over us when we feel threatened: all our attention goes to the <i>other</i>: “<i>They</i> are doing it to us: get rid of <i>them</i>.&#8221;  But this is so disempowering, for the flip side of that spell is “we have no agency, we are helpless.”  Everyone likes to be guiltless, but no one likes to be helpless.</p>
<p>Beginning in 1909 with his classic tract, <i>Hind Swaraj</i> Gandhi argued “The British did not take India; we gave her to them.”  What a wake-up call!  And he, of course, carried it out on a gigantic scale, as the double Nobel-Prize winner, Albert Szent-Gyeorgyi astutely observed: <em>“Gandhi taught the world that there are higher things than force, higher even than life itself; he proved that force had lost its suggestive power.”</em> Or rather, in our vocabulary, <i>threat </i>power had lost its suggestive force.</p>
<p>No conflict can be resolved if both parties are in an “us-vs.-them” mindframe; it behoves the nonviolent party to step out of that frame and own our own responsibility &#8212; and power.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Experiment in nonviolence: </b></p>
<p>Try this out on our own scale: the next time we feel we’re being threatened or held down, ask, &#8220;are we perhaps overlooking our own power here?&#8221;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="entry-content">
<p><strong><a href="http://mettacenter.us8.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=768c54dd5fa713b52b1623e91&amp;id=89e9ef9bef"><img class="alignleft  wp-image-15375" src="http://mettacenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Daily-Metta-250x250.png" alt="Daily Metta 250x250" width="115" height="115" /></a>Daily Metta 2015, a service of the Metta Center for Nonviolence, is a daily reflection on the strategic and spiritual insights of Mahatma Gandhi in thought, word and deed. As Gandhi called his life an “experiment in truth,” we have included an experiment in nonviolence to accompany each Daily Metta. Check in every day for new inspiration. Each year will be dedicated to another wisdom teacher.</strong></p>
</div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/whos-afraid-of-mahatma-gandhi-daily-metta/">&#8220;Who&#8217;s afraid of Gandhi?&#8221;&#8211;Daily Metta</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org">Metta Center</a>.</p>
]]></content>
			<link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/whos-afraid-of-mahatma-gandhi-daily-metta/#comments" thr:count="0"/>
		<link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/whos-afraid-of-mahatma-gandhi-daily-metta/feed/atom/" thr:count="0"/>
		<thr:total>0</thr:total>
	</entry>
		<entry>
		<author>
			<name>Stephanie Van Hook</name>
					</author>
		<title type="html"><![CDATA[&#8220;A reminder&#8221;&#8211;Daily Metta]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/a-reminder-daily-metta/" />
		<id>http://mettacenter.org/?p=16690</id>
		<updated>2015-06-05T03:08:40Z</updated>
		<published>2015-06-05T02:56:50Z</published>
		<category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="Daily Metta" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="compassion" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="daily metta" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="gandhi" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="love" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="Nonviolence" />		<summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>June 4: “We do not exaggerate when we say that life is a mere bubble.” &#8211;Gandhi (Young India, October 16, 1930) It is quite a paradox that human life is as fragile as it is powerful. Weak as we are, small as we are, our capacity for love, forgiveness, compassion, and nonviolence has no limit. From where does such power come? Gandhi compared our existence to the image of a vast ocean, where the human being is a “mere bubble” on the shore, small, insignificant, yet ever powerful, participating in something much greater than itself. Like a bubble on the shore, our power comes through us; it is greater than any one person. Such wisdom and strength to harness it is not the result of say, an advanced degree or well-toned arm muscles! It&#8217;s our destiny. The ocean does not emerge from even the millions of bubbles on the shore. The human being does not create the world; rather, existence expresses itself through us. Hello, world!  Gandhi would direct us further, “Lose yourself in the ocean of humanity. Share its dignity.” In other words, serve others, live for others, and never lose sight of respect for yourself. For the more we alienate ourselves from one another, like a drop taken from the ocean, we dry up. &#160; Experiment in Nonviolence: Your life and the life of all of those around you is precious and fragile. Remind yourself of this today. &#160; &#160; Daily Metta 2015, a service of the Metta Center for Nonviolence, is a daily reflection on the strategic and spiritual insights of Mahatma Gandhi in thought, word and deed. As Gandhi called his life an “experiment in truth,” we have included an experiment in nonviolence to accompany each Daily Metta. Check in every day for new inspiration. Each year will be dedicated to another wisdom teacher.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/a-reminder-daily-metta/">&#8220;A reminder&#8221;&#8211;Daily Metta</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org">Metta Center</a>.</p>
]]></summary>
		<content type="html" xml:base="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/a-reminder-daily-metta/"><![CDATA[<h1><b>June 4: </b></h1>
<h2><b><a href="http://mettacenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/gandhi-21.png"><img class=" size-medium wp-image-15863 alignright" src="http://mettacenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/gandhi-21-300x224.png" alt="gandhi-21" width="300" height="224" /></a>“We do not exaggerate when we say that life is a mere bubble.” </b></h2>
<p><i>&#8211;Gandhi (Young India, October 16, 1930) </i></p>
<p>It is quite a paradox that human life is as fragile as it is powerful. Weak as we are, small as we are, our capacity for love, forgiveness, compassion, and nonviolence has no limit. From where does such power come?</p>
<p>Gandhi compared our existence to the image of a vast ocean, where the human being is a “mere bubble” on the shore, small, insignificant, yet ever powerful, participating in something much greater than itself. Like a bubble on the shore, our power comes <em>through us; </em>it is greater than any one person. Such wisdom and strength to harness it is not the result of say, an advanced degree or well-toned arm muscles! It&#8217;s our destiny.</p>
<p>The ocean does not emerge from even the millions of bubbles on the shore. The human being does not create the world; rather, existence expresses itself through us. <i>Hello, world! </i></p>
<p>Gandhi would direct us further, “Lose yourself in the ocean of humanity. Share its dignity.” In other words, serve others, live for others, and never lose sight of respect for yourself. For the more we alienate ourselves from one another, like a drop taken from the ocean, we dry up.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Experiment in Nonviolence: </b></p>
<p>Your life and the life of all of those around you is precious and fragile. Remind yourself of this today.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong><a href="http://mettacenter.us8.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=768c54dd5fa713b52b1623e91&amp;id=89e9ef9bef"><img class="alignleft  wp-image-15375" src="http://mettacenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Daily-Metta-250x250.png" alt="Daily Metta 250x250" width="115" height="115" /></a>Daily Metta 2015, a service of the Metta Center for Nonviolence, is a daily reflection on the strategic and spiritual insights of Mahatma Gandhi in thought, word and deed. As Gandhi called his life an “experiment in truth,” we have included an experiment in nonviolence to accompany each Daily Metta. Check in every day for new inspiration. Each year will be dedicated to another wisdom teacher.</strong></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/a-reminder-daily-metta/">&#8220;A reminder&#8221;&#8211;Daily Metta</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org">Metta Center</a>.</p>
]]></content>
			<link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/a-reminder-daily-metta/#comments" thr:count="1"/>
		<link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/a-reminder-daily-metta/feed/atom/" thr:count="1"/>
		<thr:total>1</thr:total>
	</entry>
		<entry>
		<author>
			<name>Stephanie Van Hook</name>
					</author>
		<title type="html"><![CDATA[&#8220;When nonviolence doesn&#8217;t &#8216;work&#039;&#8221;&#8211;Daily Metta]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/when-nonviolence-doesnt-work-daily-metta/" />
		<id>http://mettacenter.org/?p=16680</id>
		<updated>2015-06-04T03:20:54Z</updated>
		<published>2015-06-04T03:13:04Z</published>
		<category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="Daily Metta" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="&quot;work&quot; vs. work" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="daily metta" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="gandhi" /><category scheme="http://mettacenter.org" term="Nonviolence" />		<summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>June 3: “Every good movement passes through five stages: indifference, ridicule, abuse, repression and respect.” &#8211;Gandhi (Young India, March 9, 1921) &#160; Many of us take for granted that a nonviolent movement will be immediately respected, but its most important &#8212; and lasting &#8212; effects are in the way our collective consciousness is awakened when we face the odds and stay the course. Gandhi maintained that only in nonviolence can you lose all of the battles and go on to win the war, and therefore if we give up too early, we lose it all! &#8220;Sorry, I tried nonviolence and it wasn’t working.&#8221; &#8220;Oh really?&#8221; Gandhi might reply. To strengthen our understanding of our power, we have to cultivate our long-term and deeper vision of how nonviolence works. At Metta, we like to talk about “work” versus work, a formula articulated by Michael Nagler. It goes like this: Violence sometimes “works” but it never works; and nonviolence sometimes “works” but it always works. In other words, in nonviolence, you don’t always attain what you set out to achieve, it does not always “work” (note use of quotes), but in the long term, it always works, it infuses positive, constructive energy into a situation, whose ripples will be felt not immediately but down the road. Nonviolence encourages, if not compels us to have faith in that powerful undercurrent that points us down the path to movement success, even if we think it’s “not working.” Experiment in Nonviolence: Think of a time when you thought a kind word or gesture, or a more developed nonviolent act, did not “work” but there were good results later on whose connection with your act may not have been obvious. &#160; Daily Metta 2015, a service of the Metta Center for Nonviolence, is a daily reflection on the strategic and spiritual insights of Mahatma Gandhi in thought, word and deed. As Gandhi called his life an “experiment in truth,” we have included an experiment in nonviolence to accompany each Daily Metta. Check in every day for new inspiration. Each year will be dedicated to another wisdom teacher.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/when-nonviolence-doesnt-work-daily-metta/">&#8220;When nonviolence doesn&#8217;t &#8216;work'&#8221;&#8211;Daily Metta</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org">Metta Center</a>.</p>
]]></summary>
		<content type="html" xml:base="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/when-nonviolence-doesnt-work-daily-metta/"><![CDATA[<h1><b>June 3:</b></h1>
<h2><b><a href="http://mettacenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/gandhi-21.png"><img class=" size-medium wp-image-15863 alignright" src="http://mettacenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/gandhi-21-300x224.png" alt="gandhi-21" width="300" height="224" /></a>“Every good movement passes through five stages: indifference, ridicule, abuse, repression and respect.” </b></h2>
<p><i>&#8211;Gandhi (Young India, March 9, 1921) </i></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Many of us take for granted that a nonviolent movement will be immediately respected, but its most important &#8212; and lasting &#8212; effects are in the way our collective consciousness is awakened when we face the odds and stay the course. Gandhi maintained that only in nonviolence can you lose all of the battles and go on to win the war, and therefore if we give up too early, we lose it all! &#8220;<i>Sorry, I tried nonviolence and it wasn’t working.&#8221; &#8220;</i><em>Oh really?&#8221; </em>Gandhi might reply.</p>
<p>To strengthen our understanding of our power, we have to cultivate our long-term and deeper vision of how nonviolence works. At Metta, we like to talk about “work” versus work, a formula articulated by Michael Nagler. It goes like this:<strong> Violence sometimes “works” but it never works; and nonviolence sometimes “works” but it <i>always </i>works.</strong> In other words, in nonviolence, you don’t always attain what you set out to achieve, it does not always “work” (note use of quotes), but in the long term, it always works, it infuses positive, constructive energy into a situation, whose ripples will be felt not immediately but down the road. Nonviolence encourages, if not compels us to have faith in that powerful undercurrent that points us down the path to movement success, even if we think it’s “not working.”<br />
<strong>Experiment in Nonviolence:</strong></p>
<p>Think of a time when you thought a kind word or gesture, or a more developed nonviolent act, did not “work” but there were good results later on whose connection with your act may not have been obvious.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong><a href="http://mettacenter.us8.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=768c54dd5fa713b52b1623e91&amp;id=89e9ef9bef"><img class="alignleft  wp-image-15375" src="http://mettacenter.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Daily-Metta-250x250.png" alt="Daily Metta 250x250" width="115" height="115" /></a>Daily Metta 2015, a service of the Metta Center for Nonviolence, is a daily reflection on the strategic and spiritual insights of Mahatma Gandhi in thought, word and deed. As Gandhi called his life an “experiment in truth,” we have included an experiment in nonviolence to accompany each Daily Metta. Check in every day for new inspiration. Each year will be dedicated to another wisdom teacher.</strong></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/when-nonviolence-doesnt-work-daily-metta/">&#8220;When nonviolence doesn&#8217;t &#8216;work'&#8221;&#8211;Daily Metta</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://mettacenter.org">Metta Center</a>.</p>
]]></content>
			<link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/when-nonviolence-doesnt-work-daily-metta/#comments" thr:count="1"/>
		<link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://mettacenter.org/daily-metta/when-nonviolence-doesnt-work-daily-metta/feed/atom/" thr:count="1"/>
		<thr:total>1</thr:total>
	</entry>
	</feed>
